HANNES BREYTENBACH

 $hannes@saao.ac.za \ +27\ 78\ 192\ 2193$



ABOUT ME

I'm a published researcher in the field of astrophysics with a passion for data science and data visualization. I am currently completing my MSc in astrophysics at University of Cape Town (UCT) and expect to graduate in December 2024.

I'm a proficient full stack python developer with 12 years of coding experience and contributions to a number of open-source scientific computing and visualization libraries. I am passionate about open source and have authored and maintain a number of software libraries for applications in astronomy. I have extensive experience in statistical model building and using machine learning to gain valuable insights into data. I have participated in, and later led independent research into developing machine learning models for predicting the onset of seizures in patients suffering from epilepsy using EEG data.

My main hobbies are outdoor adventure sports such as rock-climbing and high-lining, and I have led- and participated in numerous international expeditions to remote mountainous regions on earth.

Personal Info

Full Names: Johannes Benjamin Breytenbach

Current Occupation: MSc. Student at South African Astronomical Observatory (SAAO) &

UCT

Work Address: Room 5-42, RW James Bldg., Dept. of Astronomy, University of Cape Town

Date of Birth: 26 June 1987 Citizenship: South African

Languages: English, Afrikaans (Native); German (Conversational)

Drivers License: A, B

ONLINE PRESENCE

github.com/astromancer

 $research gate.net/profile/Hannes_Breyten bach$

kaggle.com/apodemus

stackoverflow.com/users/1098683/astromancer

in linkedin.com/in/hannes-breytenbach

 \bigstar mendeley.com/profiles/hannes-breytenbach2/

iD orcid.org/0000-0001-5391-2386

facebook.com/hannes.breytenbach.3

EDUCATION

2011 - 2024 MSc (Astrophysics) - UCT, SAAO (downgraded from PhD, completed part-time)

• Thesis title: "A Study of Quasi-Periodic Oscillations in magnetic Cataclysmic Variable Stars"

• Supervisors: Dr. David Buckley, A. Prof Patrick Wouldt

• Modules: Cataclysmic Variable Stars, Stellar Structures, Advanced General Relativity, Hot

Topics in Cosmology, High Energy Astrophysics

2010 BSc Honours (Astrophysics and Space Science) – UCT

• Thesis title: "The Sferic Count Rate from SANAE-IV, Antarctica"

• Supervisors: Dr. Andrew Collier

• Modules: General Astrophysics, Electrodynamics, General Relativity, Computational Astro-

physics, Galaxies and Large Scale Structure, Observational Techniques, Radio As-

tronomy

2006 – 2009 BSc (Physics and Astronomy) – University of Pretoria (UP)

• Project title: "Rutherford Backscattering Spectroscopy and X-ray Diffraction Spectroscopy of Alu-

minium 100"

• Supervisors: Prof. Chris Theron

• Modules: Quantum Mechanics, Solid State Physics, Statistical Mechanics, Differential Calcu-

lus, Vector Calculus, Partial Differential Equations, Abstract Algebra, Mathemati-

cal Modelling

WORK & TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021 - 2022 Python Developer / Data Scientist

Float Capital

Worked on the visualization platform for diagnostics of market system behaviour.

Researched Agent Based Modelling approach for market prediction.

2022 Tutor UCT

• Masters course: Cataclysmic Variable stars, Practical component

2009 – **2015** Tutor UCT, UP

• Tutored various subjects: Biological Physics (1st year), Astronomy (2nd year), Electrodynamics (Hons.)

2007 – 2008 Junior Data Analyst HartRAO

• Analysed radio data from astronomical masers to search for variability.

SPECIAL SKILLS

Software Development

Scientific Computing

• 2012-2024 Full stack python developer with 12 years of experience, specialising in scientific applications.

Tools: git, vscode, sourcery, pylance, pytest, tox

• 2018-2024 Contributor to matplotlib, astropy, pymultinest

Tools: github, circleCI, AWS pipelines

• 2019-2024 Author and maintainer of several open source packages: my github.

pyshoc: A library for analysing data from the Sutherland High-speed Optical Camera (SHOC) instrument.

salticam: An improved photometry pipeline for SALTICAM ultra-fast imaging camera on SALT.

Cryptocurrency

• 2021-2022 Worked on the visualization code for diagnostics of market system behaviour for the cryptocurrency trading platform Float Capital.

Tools: plotly

Data Science

Machine Learning

• 2018 – 2024 Developed obstools: A library for automated image alignment of overlapping astronomical images etc.

Skills: Image Segmentation, Image Registration, Optimization, Clustering

• 2016 Led a team in Melbourne University AES/MathWorks/NIH Seizure Prediction Challenge: Model ranked top 23% on Kaggle.

Skills: Data Mining, Feature Engineering, Model Selection, Team Management

• 2014 Developed eeg: Algorithms for classification of EEG data for American Epilepsy Society Seizure Prediction Challenge: Model ranked top 15% on Kaggle.

Skills: Time Series Analysis, Digital Signal Processing, Spectral Estimation, Statistical Modelling, Prediction, Classification

Tools: scikit-learn, tensorflow, openCV, xdg-boost

Signal Processing

• 2020 – 2024 Developed tsa: Time series analysis & spectral estimation tools to search for and characterize Quasi-Periodic Oscillations in magnetic Cataclysmic Variable stars.

Tools: scipy, astropy, pandas, sktime

Statistical Modelling

 \bullet **2020** – **2022** Developed and tested a generative model for (EM)CCD data for calibrating fast-frame rate video observations of mCVs.

Tools: pymultinest, emcee, lmfit

Cluster Computing

• 2018 Deployed pyshoc on SAAO Mensa cluster.

Tools: multiprocessing, joblib

Astronomy & Astrophysics

Observing

• 2012-2021 Total of 135 nights of observing on SAAO 1.0m, 1.9m, IRSF telescopes, including

remote operation.

Tools: Aladin, ds9, js9

• 2017 7 nights operator training on SALT.

Proposal Writing

• 2014-2015 PI of 2 successful SALT science proposals.

• 2012-2018 Co-I of several observing proposals for SAAO 1.9m, 1.0m telescopes, as well as

for the TNO telescope, National Astronomical Research Institute of Thailand

(NARIT).

Tools: LATEX, latexmk, PIPT

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

2013 - 2016	NRF, Postgraduate Development Programme (PDP) Doctoral Scholarship
2010 - 2012	South African Square Kilometre Array (SKA) Postgraduate Scholarship
2008 - 2009	SKA Undergraduate Bursary Award

LEADERSHIP & INVOLVEMENTS

Academic

2017 – 2018 Postgraduate Mentor Astronomy/Physics Dept. UCT

• Advised undergraduate students on postgraduate opportunities

2014 – 2016 Postgraduate Student Representative Astronomy Dept. UCT

• Mediated student issues within Science Faculty

• Served on Science Postgraduate student council

2011 Volunteer Siyavula Education

• Translated open source High School science textbooks into Afrikaans

Public Talks

2016 January 23 "The Cataclysmic Variables" SAAO Open Night

2016 June 20 "How the universe creates CVs" Hermanus Astronomy Club

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Conference Attendance

2023 Dec.	Magnetism & Accretion 2023	UCT Graduate Business School		
• Poster: "On the	e discovery of Quasi-Periodic oscillations in the polars J1928-5001 and IG	R J14536–5522"		
2017 Nov.	IAU Symposium 339: Southern Horizons in Time-Domain Astronomy	STIAS		
• Poster: "Quasi-	Periodic Oscillations in magnetic CVs"			
2017 Nov.	.Astronomy9	SAAO		
2017 Sept.	Deep Learning Indaba WITS			
2016 July	South African Institute of Physics (SAIP) Conference	UCT		
• Talk: "Quasi-Pe	eriodic Oscillations in magnetic CVs"			
2015 Sept.	The Golden Age of Cataclysmic Variables and Related Objects – III	Palermo, Italy		
• Talk: "Quasi-Pe	eriodic Oscillations in magnetic CVs"			
2015 June	SALT Science Conference 2015	STIAS		
• Poster: "Probin	g accretion in magnetic CVs through rapid photometry with SALTICAM	1 "		
2014 July	SAIP Conference	UJ		
• Talk: "Rapid Variability of magnetic Cataclysmic Variable Stars"				
2013 Sept.	The Golden Age of Cataclysmic Variables and Related Objects – II	Palermo, Italy		
• Talk: "Modellin	g Rapid Variability in Cataclysmic Variable Stars"			
2013 July	SKA Joint Radio Transients Conference	Protea Hotel, Krüger Gate		
2013 Feb	StellaNovae	Cape Town		
• Poster: "Modell	ling Quasi-Periodic Variability of Dwarf Novae in Outburs"			
2012 Dec.	SKA Postgraduate Bursary Conference	STIAS		
• Talk: "Modellin	g Quasi-Periodic Variability in Dwarf Novae during outburst"			
2012 Aug.	IAU XXVIII General Assembly	Beijing, China		
• Poster: "Modell	ling Quasi-Periodic Variability in Cataclysmic Variable Stars"			
2011 Dec.	SKA Postgraduate Bursary Conference	STIAS		
• Poster: "A study of DNOs and QPOs in Cataclysmic Variable Stars"				
2011 Mar.	Middle-East and African Regional IAU Meeting II (MEARIM-II)	Cape Town		
2010 – 2008 Nov.	SKA Postgraduate Bursary Conference	STIAS		

Workshop Attendance

2017 Apr. Workshop on Magnetic Accretion	SAAO		
• Talk: "Observations of Quasi-Periodic Oscillations in magnetic CVs"			
2017 Apr. SKA Big Data Africa Summer School	Cape Town		
• Led tutorial session: "Outlier detection for time series data"			
• Led a student team investigating: "Epileptic seizure prediction from EEG data"			
2016 Nov. Workshop on Bayesian Analysis in Physics and Astronomy	Stellenbosch		

• Led hack project: "Bayesian methods for CCD photometry"

$2016 \mathrm{May}$	CDS Tools Workshop	SAAO
2015 Nov.	Workshop on using ALMA for science	UCT
2015 Apr.	GPGPU programming workshop	UCT
2014 Nov.	GADGET Simulations workshop	UCT
2014 Oct.	2^{nd} Machine learning JEDI Workshop	Cape Town

• Developed classification pipeline for American Epilepsy Society Seizure Prediction Challenge

2012 Feb.	IAU Intern	national School o	of Young Astronomers (ISYA)	UCT, SAAO
0011 0 4	XX7 1 1	а а:	1 4 4 1 1	CIIDO COID D

2011 Oct. Workshop on Space Science and Astrophysics CHPC, CSIR, Pretoria

2010 Dec. Workshop on Convection in stars UJ

2010 Jan. National Astrophysics and Space Science Program (NASSP) Summer School UCT & SAAO

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed

First-Authored

[1] Discovery, observations, and modelling of a new eclipsing polar: MASTER OT J061451.70-272535.5. By H. Breytenbach, D. A. H. Buckley, P. Hakala, J. R. Thorstensen, A. Y. Kniazev, M. Motsoaledi, P. A. Woudt, S. B. Potter, V. Lipunov, E. Gorbovskoy, P. Balanutsa, and N. Tyurina. MNRAS, 484(3):3831-3845, Apr. 2019. URL: https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stz056.

Co-authored

- Two Long-period Cataclysmic Variable Stars: ASASSN-14ho and V1062 Cyg. By L. C. Gasque, C. A. Hening, R. E. Hviding, J. R. Thorstensen, K. Paterson, H. Breytenbach, M. Motsoaledi, and P. A. Woudt. AJ, 158(4):156, 156, Oct. 2019.
- [2] High-speed photometry of the eclipsing polar UZ Fornacis. By Z. N. Khangale, S. B. Potter, E. J. Kotze, P. A. Woudt, and H. Breytenbach. A&A, 621:A31, A31, Jan. 2019. URL: https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201834039.
- [3] High-speed photometry of faint cataclysmic variables IX. Targets from multiple transient surveys. By K. Paterson, P. A. Woudt, B. Warner, **H. Breytenbach**, C. K. Gilligan, M. Motsoaledi, J. R. Thorstensen, and H. L. Worters. MNRAS, 486(2):2422–2434, June 2019.
- [4] The Astropy Project: Building an Open-science Project and Status of the v2.0 Core Package. By Astropy Collaboration et al. AJ, 156(3):123, 123, Sept. 2018. URL: https://doi.org/10.3847%2F1538-3881%2Faabc4f.
- [5] Optical Studies of 15 Hard X-Ray Selected Cataclysmic Binaries. By J. P. Halpern, J. R. Thorstensen, P. Cho, G. Collver, M. Motsoaledi, H. Breytenbach, D. A. H. Buckley, and P. A. Woudt. AJ, 155(6):247, 247, June 2018. URL: https://doi.org/10.3847%2F1538-3881%2Faabfd0.
- [6] The Structure of Chariklo's Rings from Stellar Occultations. By D. Bérard et al. AJ, 154:144, 144, Oct. 2017. URL: http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/aa830d/meta.
- [7] Size and Shape of Chariklo from Multi-epoch Stellar Occultations. By R. Leiva, B. Sicardy, J. I. B. Camargo, J.-L. Ortiz, J. Desmars, D. Bérard, E. Lellouch, E. Meza, P. Kervella, C. Snodgrass, R. Duffard, N. Morales, A. R. Gomes-Júnior, G. Benedetti-Rossi, R. Vieira-Martins, F. Braga-Ribas, M. Assafin, B. E. Morgado, F. Colas, C. De Witt, A. A. Sickafoose, H. Breytenbach, J.-L. Dauvergne, P. Schoenau, L. Maquet, K.-L. Bath, H.-J. Bode, A. Cool, B. Lade, S. Kerr, and D. Herald. AJ, 154:159, 159, Oct. 2017. URL: http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/aa8956/meta.

[8] A VLT-ULTRACAM study of the fast optical quasi-periodic oscillations in the polar V834 Centauri. By M. Mouchet, J.-M. Bonnet-Bidaud, L. Van Box Som, E. Falize, D. A. H. Buckley, H. Breytenbach, R. P. Ashley, T. R. Marsh, and V. S. Dhillon. A&A, 600:A53, A53, Apr. 2017. URL: https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/abs/2017/04/aa30166-16/aa30166-16.html.

- [9] IGR J19552+0044: A new asynchronous short period polar. Filling the gap between intermediate and ordinary polars. By G. Tovmassian, D. González-Buitrago, J. Thorstensen, E. Kotze, H. Breytenbach, A. Schwope, F. Bernardini, S. V. Zharikov, M. S. Hernandez, D. A. H. Buckley, E. de Miguel, F.-J. Hambsch, G. Myers, W. Goff, D. Cejudo, D. Starkey, T. Campbell, J. Ulowetz, W. Stein, P. Nelson, D. E. Reichart, J. B. Haislip, K. M. Ivarsen, A. P. LaCluyze, J. P. Moore, and A. S. Miroshnichenko. A&A, 608:A36, A36, Dec. 2017. URL: https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201731323.
- [10] Peculiarities of the accretion flow in the system HL CMa. By A. Semena, M. Revnivtsev, D. Buckley, A. Lutovinov, and **H. Breytenbach**. Astronomy Letters, 42(6):379–392, 2016. URL: https://arxiv.org/pdf/1610.00874.pdf.
- [11] High-speed photometry of faint cataclysmic variables-VIII. Targets from the Catalina Real-Time Transient Survey. By D. L. Coppejans, P. A. Woudt, B. Warner, E. Körding, S. A. Macfarlane, M. P. Schurch, M. M. Kotze, H. Breytenbach, A. A. Gulbis, and R. Coppejans. MNRAS, 437(1):510-523, 2014. URL: https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/437/1/510/1001483/High-speed-photometry-of-faint-cataclysmic.
- [12] On the area of accretion curtains from fast aperiodic time variability of the intermediate polar EX Hya. By A. N. Semena, M. G. Revnivtsev, D. A. Buckley, M. M. Kotze, I. I. Khabibullin, **H. Breytenbach**, A. A. Gulbis, R. Coppejans, and S. B. Potter. MNRAS, 442(2):1123-1132, 2014. URL: https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article-abstract/442/2/1123/981562/On-the-area-of-accretion-curtains-from-fast.

Conference Proceedings

- [1] High time resolution variability, optical photometry and polarimetry studies of magnetic CVs. By D. Buckley, T. Marsh, J.-M. Bonnet-Bidaud, M. Mouchet, V. Dhillon, H. Breytenbach, P. Irawati, S. Potter, M. Motsoaledi, and P. Woudt. In 42nd COSPAR Scientific Assembly, volume 42, E1.7-10-18, E1.7-10-18, July 2018.
- [2] MASTER-SAAO transient detections: new Cataclysmic Variable discoveries. By D. A. H. Buckley, H. Breyten-bach, A. Kniazev, M. Kotze, M. Motsoaledi, S. Potter, P. Woudt, V. Lipunov, and E. Gorbovskoy. In Proceedings of Science, 2017. URL: https://pos.sissa.it/archive/conferences/255/027/Golden2015_027.pdf.
- [3] Quasi-periodic oscillations in magnetic Cataclysmic Variables: Results for V834 Cen. By H. Breytenbach, Buckley, D. A. H., Bonnet-Bidaud, J.-M., and Mouchet, M. In Proceedings of Science, 2017. URL: https://pos.sissa.it/archive/conferences/255/018/Golden2015_018.pdf.
- [4] New Observations of Accretion Phenomena in Magnetic Cataclysmic Variables. By D. Buckley, S. Potter, E. Kotze, M. Kotze, and H. Breytenbach. In EPJ Web of Conferences, volume 64, page 07005. EDP Sciences, 2014. URL: www.epj-conferences.org/articles/epjconf/pdf/2014/01/epjconf_mag2013_07005.pdf.

Short publications

- [1] Classification of MASTER OT J061451. 70-272535.5 as an eclipsing Polar. By D. Buckley, **H. Breytenbach**, A. Kniazev, M. Kotze, M. Motsoaledi, S. Potter, J. Thorstensen, E. Gorbovskoy, V. Lipunov, and P. Woudt. The Astronomer's Telegram, 7169:1, 2015. URL: http://www.astronomerstelegram.org/?read=7169.
- [2] SALT spectroscopy of the flaring blazar J141922. 55-083832.0. By D. Buckley, H. Breytenbach, A. Kniazev, M. Kotze, S. Potter, E. Gorbovskoy, and V. Lipunov. The Astronomer's Telegram, 7167:1, 2015. URL: http://www.astronomerstelegram.org/?read=7167.

Outreach & Volunteering

2024 Public Stargazing

• Hosted public stargazing event at the Rocklands Highline Festival

2023 Public Stargazing

• Hosted public stargazing event at the Namaqua Flower Festival

2023-2024 Metal work

Clean Green Muizenberg

• Community project to make trash bins for the local park from upcycled oil drums

2013 – **2020** Volunteer

SAAO

• Volunteer at SAAO Open Night and various public stargazing events

2018

• Hosted public stargazing event at the Festival of Friends, Natures Valley

2017-2018 Founding Member & Sport Climbing Coach DreamHigher NPO

• Coach Rock Climbing to previously disadvantaged young adults

2012 – 2015 Mountain Search and Rescue Member

Mountain Club of South Africa (MCSA)

SPORTS & CULTURE

2022 Project lead

South African Highline Record

• Established the longest highline in SA at 460m in Mosselbay

2011 – **2015** Committee member

UCT Mountain and Ski Club (MSC)

• Fulfilled various portfolio roles including Expeditions, Equipment and Ski

2014 Chairperson

UCT MSC

- Led a committee of 22 people at the head of a society with 800 members
- Managed and spent a budget of $\sim R250~000$
- Coordinated 5-10 weekly events

2013 Expedition Leader

UCT MSC

- Led Team on MSC expedition to summit Mt Kenya (5 199m)
- Awarded R 14 000 in sponsorship funding

2012 Sports Merit Award

UCT

Led Southern-African team on UIAA Youth expedition to summit the highest mountain in Europe, Mt Elbrus (5 642m)

2011 Sports Performance of the Year Award UCT

- Co-organised mountaineering expedition to summit the Himalayan peak, CB13-A (6 264m)
- Awarded R 30 000 in sponsorship funding
- Article in UCT Campus Sport Magazine

2010 – present Waaihoek Leader

UCT MSC

• Organised and lead numerous international expeditions and multi-day hikes

REFERENCES

Prof. Patrick Woudt

Head of Department Astronomy, UCT pwoudt@ast.uct.ac.za $+27\ 21\ 650\ 2392$

Prof. Bruce Bassett

 $\label{lem:cosmology} \begin{tabular}{l}{l}{Head of Cosmology and Machine Learning group, African Institute for Mathematical Sciences bruce.a.bassett@gmail.com\\ \end{tabular}$

Jason Smythe

Cofounder, Float Capital jason@float.capital